<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
        <channel>
                <title>blog.torresmateo.com</title>
                <description>Rants, computational biology, and software development.</description>
                <link>http://localhost:4000</link>
                <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
                
                        <item>
                                <title>How to setup Zotero on multiple computers and OSs</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;Since the beginning of the PhD, I knew I needed a better way to handle a library than collecting a huge file with BibTeX entries. However, I was not happy with most reference management software. Mostly because rather sooner than later it felt like I could not really have the control I wanted. Unless (of course) I started paying them for features such as storing my files in the cloud, or syncing the entries across multiple computers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, I went with the not-so-fully-featured-but-free option: &lt;a href=&quot;zotero.org&quot;&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt;, and never looked back. Configuring it for my use case, however, was not an easy task. I needed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A library that I can access from my laptop (a Mac), my lab workstation (dual boot Windows and Ubuntu), and the iPad.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My annotations to be synced across all of these platforms (so, all of them should be pointing to the same version of the file)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A solution compatible with Google Drive.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I wanted to keep the file structure I was manually handling to be maintained. Because then (and at the time of writing) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zotero.org/support/ios_beta&quot;&gt;Zotero does not have an iOS app&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A way to avoid manually adding 400+ papers and books to Zotero.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is the step-by-step guide on how to achieve all of these without spending a week fiddling with all the plugins and configurations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-install-the-necessary-plugins&quot;&gt;1. Install the necessary plugins&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll need two plugins:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://zotfile.com/&quot;&gt;ZotFile&lt;/a&gt;: This plugin will take care of renaming the PDFs based on fields of the paper, as well as keeping the folder structure coherent with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zotero.org/support/collections_and_tags&quot;&gt;Zotero Collections&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/retorquere/zotero-folder-import&quot;&gt;Folder Import&lt;/a&gt;: You need this plugin only if you want to avoid importing several papers manually. (You will need to install this one only on the computer where you want to build the first Zotero Library, in all other computers you will get all the items synced automatically).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To install a plugin, simply download the latest version of each (these are files with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;xpi&lt;/code&gt; extension), open Zotero and go to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Tools &amp;gt;&amp;gt; Add-ons&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/zotero-guide/tools-menu.png&quot; alt=&quot;tools-menu&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will open the Add-ons Manager dialogue. Go ahead and select &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&quot;Install Add-on From File...&quot;&lt;/code&gt;, navigate to the directory where the plugins were downloaded, and restart Zotero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/zotero-guide/add-ons-manager.png&quot; alt=&quot;add-ons-manager&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-set-the-base-directory&quot;&gt;2. Set the Base Directory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a critical part of the setup, as it’s the one setting that will allow your library to be correctly linked across operating systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default, Zotero points to files using absolute paths. If this is the case, you will need to ensure that every computer has the &lt;em&gt;exact&lt;/em&gt; same path in order for the files to be linked correctly. Luckily, this can be easily overridden by setting the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Linked Attachment Base Directory&lt;/code&gt; to point somewhere we want. In my case, that’s Google Drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To set this up, open the Zotero Preferences, go to the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Advanced&lt;/code&gt; tab, and then to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Files and Folders&lt;/code&gt;. Click &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Choose...&lt;/code&gt;, and select a cloud folder that will be synchronized by your cloud provider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/zotero-guide/base-directory.png&quot; alt=&quot;base-directory&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Zotero will still copy files into its default directory, and ZotFile will rename and move that file to the Base Directory, and change the entry in the library. The entry will now point to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zotero.org/support/attaching_files#stored_files_and_linked_files&quot;&gt;Linked File&lt;/a&gt; (as opposed to a Stored File).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-zotfile-configuration&quot;&gt;3. ZotFile configuration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will be using ZotFile to rename and move all files from the default Zotero directory to the Base Directory, and update the library entry with a link to the moved file. However, ZotFile does not asume that this is the use case we want, and therefore we need to tell it where we want the files to go. For this, we need to set &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Location of Files&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&quot;Custom Location&quot;&lt;/code&gt; and choose the same directory we chose as our Base Directory. It is very important that we choose the same folder, or the linked files will not work correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/zotero-guide/zotfile-general-settings.png&quot; alt=&quot;zotfile-general-settings&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to retain the subfolder structure of the Base Directory the same as the collections in Zotero, you should also set check the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Use subfolder defined by&lt;/code&gt; option, and set the value to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/%c&lt;/code&gt;, which is the ZotFile &lt;a href=&quot;http://zotfile.com/#renaming-rules&quot;&gt;wildcard&lt;/a&gt; corresponding to “collection path”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;optional-renaming-rules&quot;&gt;(OPTIONAL) Renaming Rules&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, a very important part of managing the library is setting names that are easy to navigate. Both Zotero and ZotFile have the ability to rename files based on metadata available for the particular paper. You can use either, but I chose to stick with ZotFile as &lt;a href=&quot;https://forums.zotero.org/discussion/89402/zotfile-vs-zotero-renaming&quot;&gt;it’s more versatile&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recommend you take a couple of minutes and learn the &lt;a href=&quot;http://zotfile.com/#renaming-rules&quot;&gt;wildcards&lt;/a&gt; to build your own. I use the following renaming pattern:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;({\%y}) - [{\%w}] - {\%a} -- {\%t}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is, the year &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;{\%y}&lt;/code&gt; in parentheses, the journal &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;{\%w}&lt;/code&gt; in square brackets, the authors &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;{\%a}&lt;/code&gt;, and finally the title &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;{\%t}&lt;/code&gt;, everything separated by one or two hyphens. I like this because it is efective for me to sort papers in chronological order quickly, and it helps me navigate large collections on the iPad. Here’s how the remaining options look for me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/zotero-guide/zotfile-renaming-rules.png&quot; alt=&quot;zotfile-renaming-rules&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-populate-the-library&quot;&gt;4. Populate the Library&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step is to “ingest” your existing PDFs into the Library. However, feel free to go to the skip to step 6 if you prefer to start your library from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, we will use the Folder Import plugin, which added the “Add Files from Ffolder” option under the “New Item” menu in Zotero (the green icon on top of the main pane)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/zotero-guide/add-files-from-folder.png&quot; alt=&quot;add-files-from-folder&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click that one, and select the folder that contains your existing files. You will be presented with a dialog where you tell the plugin wich formats should be copied:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/zotero-guide/extension-dialog.png&quot; alt=&quot;extension-dialog&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Select all the extensions from the detected ones, and click OK. The copying process should take a couple of minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-moving-everything-to-the-cloud-with-zotfile&quot;&gt;5. Moving everything to the cloud with ZotFile&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once every paper is already in Zotero, it’s time to finally move everything to the cloud folder. This should be as painless as selecting “My Library” (the top-level collection):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/zotero-guide/my-library.png&quot; alt=&quot;my-library&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, on the main pane, select all items, right-click on the selection, and under “Manage Attachments” click on “Rename and Move”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/zotero-guide/rename-and-move.png&quot; alt=&quot;rename-and-move&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;you’ll be presented with a dialog asking if you’re sure you want to process a big number of papers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/zotero-guide/confirm-dialog.png&quot; alt=&quot;confirm-dialog&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confirm, and watch your cloud folder be populated with nicely renamed and sorted PDFs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-synchronize-the-library-across-multiple-zotero-installatations&quot;&gt;6. Synchronize the Library across multiple Zotero installatations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’re happy with the initial library, and all files are renamed and organized in a cloud folder, you can safely create a Zotero account, and sync the library across multiple installations. Remember to &lt;a href=&quot;#2-set-the-base-directory&quot;&gt;set the base directory&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;#3-zotfile-configuration&quot;&gt;configure ZotFile&lt;/a&gt; on the new installation before logging into your account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;7-final-tips&quot;&gt;7. Final tips:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Zotero has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zotero.org/download/&quot;&gt;excellent extensions&lt;/a&gt; for all major browsers which add a very convenient button to download the paper from the web. Once the item is added, ZotFile automatically renames the paper and places the linked file in the right directory.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can have multiple files associated with the same item in Zotero. I use this when I need to keep a “clean” version of a book or paper for sharing with colleagues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 06:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://localhost:4000//zotero-guide/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//zotero-guide/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Discutamos mejor</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;Primeramente, confieso que soy un analfabeto en lo que a política respecta. Sin embargo, estuve siguiendo en estos días el tema de los &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ultimahora.com/camioneros-t&quot;&gt;camioneros&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lanacion.com.py/search/camioneros/?q=camioneros&quot;&gt;vs.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.abc.com.py/tag/camioneros-4555.html&quot;&gt;bitrenes&lt;/a&gt; en Paraguay. Este es un caso que me parece resume muchas cosas que podemos mejorar los paraguayos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;el-caso-en-cuestión&quot;&gt;El caso en cuestión&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Un brevísimo (e incompleto) resumen de lo que ocurrió (con links a los detalles):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;El Ministerio de Obras Públicas y Comunicaciones &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mopc.gov.py/mopc-autoriza-de-forma-experimental-circulacion-de-bitrenes-en-un-tramo-de-la-ruta-v-n5452&quot;&gt;aprueba &lt;strong&gt;experimentalmente&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; el uso de bitrenes en un tramo de una de las rutas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Esta resolución (que no logré encontrar en Internet) es aplaudida por diversos &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.abc.com.py/nacionales/comerciantes-e-industriales-apoyan-ingreso-de-bitrenes-1669829.html&quot;&gt;comerciantes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;El gremio de camioneros se manifiesta en contra de la resolución a través de paros, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ultimahora.com/continua-el-bloqueo-rutas-y-empresarios-n1131677.html&quot;&gt;bloqueos&lt;/a&gt; y huelgas (lo típico)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;El MOPC y los interesados en bitrenes defienden la aprobación de su uso y el usual ping pong de (paupérrimos) artículos de prensa inundan el día a día.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mi intención en este caso NO es disuadir a nadie a favor o en contra del uso de bitrenes. En vez de esto, quiero llevar la atención al hecho de que en la avalancha de artículos publicados por los mayores periódicos del país, se hace mínima alusión a motivos reales por los cuales uno podría objetivamente estar a favor o en contra de la situación. En su gran mayoría, los artículos se enfocan en una mezcla de:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A quienes beneficiaría personalmente permitir bitrenes, usualmente mostrando a grandes empresarios y políticos como beneficiarios directos.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Al hecho de que los camioneros quedarían irremediablemente reemplazados y obsoletos, y lo injusto que esto es.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reportes de las quejas de la ciudadanía en respuesta a los paros y medidas de presión del gremio de camioneros.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Puntos a favor defendiendo al MOPC y al uso de bitrenes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;La potencial falta de cerveza a causa del paro (una de las noticias de todo este tema con más vistas y más comentarios).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entre todo esto, me parece que hay puntos clave que se vuelven evidentes en la conversación (en twitter y facebook):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Primeramente, NADIE (ni el MOPC, ni los camioneros, ni el público en general) provee datos estadísticos o estudios de suelo o evidencia alguna que soporte su punto de vista:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;El lenguaje usual de un “pro-camionero” es absolutamente fatalista:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;el camionero definitivamente pierde su trabajo&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;una vez más estamos “dándole todo” a los brasileros (como siempre!)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;los únicos beneficiados serán (una vez más) los políticos de turno y empresarios mega millonarios.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;El lenguaje de un “pro-bitrenes” es usualmente:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;introducir bitrenes en Paraguay es claramente la MEJOR decisión alguna vez tomada por seres humanos.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;innumerables beneficios como:
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;más trabajo en el país&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;mejores precios para el transporte de mercaderías&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;estar en contra es claramente ser un zurdo anti progresista (de mierda).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;la-conversación-en-general&quot;&gt;La conversación en general&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Como con toda falsa dicotomía, hechos como que esta aprobación sea experimental quedan totalmente relegados a discusiones sobre política partidaria y el hecho o no de que alguien sea “zurdo comunista” o “imperialista privilegiado”. En la realidad, dudo que la situación sea simple de resolver, y me parece que no hay públicamente disponible suficiente evidencia acerca de si conviene o no aprobar los bitrenes. La discusión actual esta claramente basada en “hechos” adoptados por ambos bandos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El nivel de conversación en Paraguay hace evidente el motivo por el cual la corrupción es ubicua. Sencillamente, no nos preocupamos por saber la verdad. Es suficiente que &lt;strong&gt;los otros&lt;/strong&gt; “pierdan” la discusión. Tristemente, esto es algo que se da muchas veces en la conversación en Paraguay, y me temo que esto da pié al “juego político” en que se toman decisiones para complacer a la población basados en opiniones sin fundamento. Basta que la conversación original (sobre bitrenes) derive a la usual conversación de “colorados vs. liberales” o “zurdos vs. imperialistas” para que el tema central quede absolutamente relegado. Es esta incapacidad de mantener la atención en lo central de la cuestión (bitrenes en este caso) lo que habilita a los mal intencionados a usar al pueblo como marionetas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Si en lugar de gritarnos mutuamente exigiéramos datos que nos ayuden a tener un argumento real a la hora de discutir, progresaríamos una barbaridad. Si en lugar de señalar al otro intentáramos entender su punto de vista, llegaríamos al menos un paso más lejos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;discutamos-el-progreso&quot;&gt;Discutamos el progreso&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Si el nivel de la conversación pública pudiera elevarse a discutir el tema en cuestión, estaríamos discutiendo el progreso del país. Este progreso es posible a pesar de la política (de mierda) que tenemos.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                                <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2018 16:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://localhost:4000//discutamos-mejor/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//discutamos-mejor/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Particle WHAT?!</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the most frequent questions that I get is: “What is it that you did before?”. And the answer to that question always ends up in what my thesis was about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the title of my thesis is “Particle Swarm Optimisation for solving many-objective problems”. This most often than not results in people just saying something like “riiiiight”. It is a bit frustrating not being able to share with everyone what is it that I actually did. This post is an attempt to explain it in simple terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;optimisation&quot;&gt;Optimisation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, to optimise something means to make it effective or efficient as much as possible. This means that we usually want to make something as big or as little as possible. For instance,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want to optimise the amount of money I spend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want to spend as &lt;u&gt;**little**&lt;/u&gt; as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want to optimise the amount of money I make&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want to earn as &lt;u&gt;**much**&lt;/u&gt; as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that, depending on the case, to optimise something means to either &lt;strong&gt;maximise&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;minimise&lt;/strong&gt; it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;many-objective&quot;&gt;Many-objective&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is perhaps the most difficult piece to explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An optimisation problem can have only one objective if we want to maximise or minimise only one thing. This is fine for simple problems, but it is not enough to model real life problems. The bigger problems tend to have several things that we want to optimise. For instance, when selecting which route to take when driving home, we want the route that is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;fastest&lt;/strong&gt; (to get sooner).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;shortest&lt;/strong&gt; (to spend less petrol).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;cheapest&lt;/strong&gt; (in the case of toll roads).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;safest&lt;/strong&gt; (if you live in a place with high crime rate).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At least &lt;strong&gt;one drive-thru on the way&lt;/strong&gt; (it is perhaps time for a snack).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might not be super obvious at a first glance that these objectives are possibly conflicting. In rush hour, for instance, the shortest way might not be the fastest or the safest. As a consequence, a situation can arise in which you have two routes that are identically “good”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Route A will take 20 minutes in rush-hour, but it will cost 20£ of petrol because it’s long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Route B will take 30 minutes in rush-hour, but it will cost only 10£ because it’s short.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are 2 possible solutions to the problem, and the decision between them is not obvious. If the long route was as cheap as the short one, then that is the best solution for sure, but now we have no option but to choose to have a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;long-but-fast&lt;/code&gt; route or a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;short-but-slow&lt;/code&gt; one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we have more than 3 objectives to optimise, we have a many-objective problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#Particle Swarm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we know now what a many-objective problem is, and it’s kind of clear that they can be massively difficult to solve. Also, if you want to add more objectives it only gets harder. This motivated super intelligent people into thinking “so… what can we do to actually find solutions when we have a gazillion objectives?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several things were proposed to solve this kind of problems. Some of them work kind of well. The one my thesis is based on is inspired by the behaviour of swarms of bees and pigeons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know, this is super cool!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So… what is it that the bees and pigeons do that is so cool to solve this kind of problem? They perform a collaborative search for food or shelter in a big space, and they do that in big groups. If a bee finds a particular place full of tasty flowers, she will tell all the swarm something like “hey guys, I’ve found some awesome flowers!”. The rest of the swarm will be attracted to that particular place and after some time all of the swarm will be happily feeding in a particular garden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we take this behaviour to the routes example, we can think of the same kind of method to solve our issue. We have many virtual “bees” that we call “particles”. They look for possible routes in the space of all possible ways home. When one of the particles finds a short path, all the other particles will be looking for even shorter paths and will be attracted by that solution. After a while, just like the real bees, the particles are overflying a particular spot in the space and that is the set of possible solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-we-actually-did&quot;&gt;What we actually did&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our job in all this thing was to implement the Particle Swarm solution to solve a set of many-objective problems. We compared that algorithm to a genetic algorithm that is the best algorithm to solve this kind of problems at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We showed that although the genetic algorithm comes up with better solutions for some problems, the swarm approach comes with better solutions in other problems and in a fraction of the time it takes the genetic algorithm to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, here you have a video I made of some (red) particles finding the (blue) solution on a 3D space :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/YEgvX7X80x8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in this stuff, please contact me. I’m more than happy to talk about it. There is a LOT that can be done with this kind of algorithms, and there is wide range of practical problems that can be tackled using them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re not happy with this explanation contact me as well and I’ll try to improve it!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2016 06:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://localhost:4000//mopso/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//mopso/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Un buen juez</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;Unos días atrás estuve conversando con unos amigos sobre cualquier pavada en un grupo de WhatsApp. No recuerdo exactamente cómo, pero en algún momento la conversación se torna en una conversación acerca de como está el país y se inicia un ping pong de ideas. Convencionalmente esto terminaría en un ping pong de ideas políticas con diferentes grados de tendencias a la derecha o izquierda… pero no esta vez.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hablamos de las ventajas y desventajas de la forma en que se maneja la justicia y se resuelven los conflictos en Paraguay, y como siempre esta discusión estaba bajo la sombra de la siempre presente corrupción y amiguismo que acompaña en la vida real todo el proceso.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En algún punto de la conversación propuse que se deje en manos de una computadora la resolución de casos simples y cuyos resultados sean obvios…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;¿Una locura… verdad?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Este post es acerca de porqué yo creo que esto no es tan loco como parece y algunas ideas iniciales de cómo podría implementarse un “juez electrónico”. Me enfoco en los principales obstáculos de la implementación.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;la-lógica-de-la-justicia-la-ley&quot;&gt;La lógica de la justicia (la ley)&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Las leyes se basan en la lógica… En particular, en la lógica jurídica. La lógica jurídica a su vez depende del lenguaje en que están escritos los artículos y esta por supuesto sujeta a interpretación debido a las ambigüedades del lenguaje. Esto en mi opinión es razonable si asumimos que el juez es incorruptible e imparcial. En la vida real (y especialmente en Paraguay) esto no ocurre. Por lo tanto, se requiere de una lógica formal y no contradictoria que pueda modelar la ley actual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ciertamente modelar la lógica jurídica con artículos muy generales y sus miles de posibles interpretaciones es una tarea compleja. Pero el juez digital no precisa de esto, ya que existe una parte no contradictoria en la ley que es posible modelar como una lógica formal. Aunque el juez digital no pueda resolver los casos más complejos, podría alivianar la carga a seres humanos o al menos dar sugerencias fundamentadas en la ley en conflictos menores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En mi opinión esto es más que suficiente para mejorar sustancialmente la justicia en Paraguay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;machine-learning-y-big-data&quot;&gt;Machine Learning y Big Data&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La ciencia de la computación en estos días es tal que permite utilizar la experiencia en otros campos para tomar mejores decisiones. En sus inicios esto estaba limitado por la escasez de datos disponibles para inferir cualquier tipo de patrón.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hoy en día sin embargo, la cantidad de información disponible en cualquier campo de investigación es sin duda abrumadora para cualquier ser humano. Pero se ha demostrado (con &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AlphaGo&quot;&gt;AlphaGo&lt;/a&gt; por ejemplo) que se vuelve posible este tipo de decisiones de forma exitosa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;el-juez-perfecto&quot;&gt;El juez perfecto&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quizás el punto principal y más importante del juez digital es que no propongo un juez perfecto. Sólo propongo un juez que sea más justo y eficiente que el sistema actual. Estoy muy de acuerdo en que la tarea de hacer un juez automático que compita con un ser humano incorruptible es casi imposible. Pero teniendo en cuenta que hoy en día la justicia en Paraguay es en muchos casos un absurdo extremo, no veo porqué no darle una oportunidad a esta idea. Al final de cuentas, a este juez no se le va a poder comprar.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2016 07:17:00 +0100</pubDate>
                                <link>http://localhost:4000//un-buen-juez/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//un-buen-juez/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>First Month in the UK</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been a while since I updated this thingy… Hello!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tonight it’s all about my first month in the UK. For a brief summary: I’m starting a PhD in Computer Science (Bioinformatics) at Royal Holloway, University of London. It will take four years counting from September 2015 (yes, I arrived a little bit late, more details below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;im-going-on-an-adventure&quot;&gt;I’m going on an adventure!&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving home is always exiting and frankly quite scary, especially since I never really spent long periods of time away from home. I was especially aware of everything thanks to both my mother and my sister (who are the ones that usually travel a lot in my family) who literally packed a lot of stuff in the suitcases that I thought were unnecessary but I was (obviously) utterly wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arriving here was quite a challenge, even after I had accepted the offer from Royal Holloway. The visa process takes a really long time and I had to go to Buenos Aires just to provide the required documents, and after that they process everything in Bogotá! (I hope they have a very good reason to spend so much in posting documents around instead of hiring some people to process the documents locally, but that’s not the point today). Nevertheless, I made it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;i-can-cook-after-all&quot;&gt;I can cook after all&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things I am proud of is the fact that I can actually cook! (And this means more than assemble some ingredients into a sandwich or a pizza at best). But behold!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/uk/first-month/fugazza.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
This is a fugazza I made on the second weekend (and I realised I didn’t have a rolling pin!). It tasted very good!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/uk/first-month/tuna-thing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
This is.. a … tuna thing! (or tuna cake, or tuna bread). I tried in the first weekend here when I went to my supervisor’s house for a party. We were all so delighted by this that we asked for the recipe and I made it! (It wasn’t as good as the original one, but it tasted good nonetheless).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-place&quot;&gt;The Place&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I live in Egham, just outside London. It is far greener than I expected and walking is easier than in Asunción (because weather is not inhumanly hot). Here are 4 pictures of my first walk around Egham and Englefield Green (the town next to Egham).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/uk/first-month/egham1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/uk/first-month/egham2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/uk/first-month/egham3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/uk/first-month/egham4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;royal-holloway-university-of-london&quot;&gt;Royal Holloway, University of London&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is beyond my ability to find the right words to describe the University, so… pictures!
&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/uk/first-month/rhul1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/uk/first-month/rhul2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/uk/first-month/rhul3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/uk/first-month/rhul4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-lab&quot;&gt;The Lab&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m currently in the Computer Science Department at Royal Holloway, working in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paccanarolab.org&quot;&gt;PaccanaroLab&lt;/a&gt; (run by Alberto Paccanaro, my supervisor).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People here is amazing, right now we are mostly from Paraguay (check the “people” section in the website) and I feel very good working with everybody! Also, I get to work in the same place as the creator of the amazing tool &lt;a href=&quot;http://igraph.org&quot;&gt;igraph&lt;/a&gt; used to work, which is AWESOME!!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                                <pubDate>Mon, 09 Nov 2015 20:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://localhost:4000//first-month-in-the-UK/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//first-month-in-the-UK/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>¿Porqué me quedo colgado de repente?</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;En medio de una conversación fluida de repente PAF!, me quedo (aparentemente) congelado unos segundos antes de responder. Claramente
esto afecta al ritmo de la conversación y a veces incluso genera que se pierda el &lt;em&gt;rapport&lt;/em&gt; que había hasta ese microsegundo anterior
a que me quede colgado. Estoy seguro de que no solo me pasa a mi… pero ultimamente la verdaaad es que cada vez me lo hacen notar con
más frecuencia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Para no dar muchas vueltas, la realidad es que en esos momentos NO me quedo colgado, pero estoy considerando que responder, y quizás 
estoy considerando &lt;em&gt;varias&lt;/em&gt; cosas que responder. Algo que no me explico es ¿como es que esto se da en conversaciones triviales de 
la vida? Sinceramente, NI IDEA…. PERO!! Tengo una teoría de porque me pasa a mi (y quizás también sea así para vos!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cada vez es más necesario para mí hacerme muchas preguntas. Esto se debe principalmente a que me estoy dedicando un poco más a la 
investigación y a diseñar soluciones a diverso tipo de problemas (informáticos por lo general). Este ejercicio mental hace que la
mayor parte de mi actividad productiva sea “dentro” de mi cabeza. Me gusta pensar que estoy progresando porque cada vez puedo considerar
más factores al encarar un problema y las soluciones resultantes se vuelven mas “elegantes” que las soluciones que proponía hace un 
año.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me parece que un efecto de estar mucho tiempo pensando de esta manera, hace que ante cualquier trivialidad tienda a analizar cada vez
más factores dentro del contexto de la conversación. El efecto de esto? Estoy ahi como una computadora cuando se cuelga… &lt;em&gt;sin un
output&lt;/em&gt; que de evidencia de que sigo en el “mundo real”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#¿Es esto algo negativo?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Si. Mantener una conversación fluida es un aspecto muy importante de la vida del ser humano. Y pensar mucho en algo innecesario es una
pérdida de energía y tiempo que finalmente no lleva a nada. Ciertamente nada es absoluto y hay ocasiones en las que uno tiene que 
considerar muchas cosas antes de responder (como por ejemplo una entrevista de trabajo, un debate, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#¿Que puedo hacer al respecto?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personalmente, trato conscientemente de no irme mucho por las ramas de pensamiento cuando estoy conversando. Cuando creo que es algo
demasiado importante como para evitar pensar bastante antes de responder, trato de dar algún tipo de &lt;em&gt;feedback&lt;/em&gt; al interlocutor (algo
como “Dejame pensar un ratito” o ponerme un una típica pose de pensador, como agarrarme la barba).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#¿Eso funciona?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Más o menos. Este ejercicio mental hace que disminuya en cierto grado el corte en la fluidez de las conversaciones que tengo 
cotidianamente. Si te pasa algo similar, te cuento que es un poco frustrante no tener la libertad de pensar mucho antes de responder 
y “arriesgarte” a dar una respuesta de la que después te puedas arrepentir. Pero ayuda un poco pensar que hablar en “tiempo real” es 
una habilidad muy buena, y optimizar la cantidad de pensamiento que se da a un tema antes de responder es una habilidad muy deseable 
para la vida.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Advertencia: Este es un post basado en opiniones y una investigación informal y poco profunda de un tema que no conozco muy bien.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2015 07:17:00 +0100</pubDate>
                                <link>http://localhost:4000//quedarse-colgado/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//quedarse-colgado/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Ingeniería, la vida... y World of Warcraft</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;Buenas a todos!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Después de 5 meses y alguito decidí invertir un poco de tiempo en renovar el blog y justificar lo que gasté en el dominio!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pasaron muchas cosas desde enero y van a ver en las siguientes secciones todo lo que estuve haciendo desde enero hasta acá, incluyendo algunas cosas de antes de enero que
no incluí en otros posts porque no quería mezclar tanto temas generales con desarrollo de videojuegos y cosas de informática en general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Antes de seguir con el post, enumero los cambios al blog que vinieron con este post!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Mejora general del estilo (desde mi punto de vista de programador!).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Sección en Español (para este tipo de posts que son más para mi familia/amigos que manuales de informática y cosas así). Prometo arreglar eventualmente los errores ortográficos!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Algunas cosas van a cambiar en el futuro, sobre todo cuando decida dedicarme un poco más a la parte visual del blog. Por ahora me parece cómodo de leer :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#Ingeniería!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Altas probabilidades de que si me conocés sabes que hace mas o menos un mes finalmente defendí la tesis :D. Fue un proceso largo (un poco más de dos años)
y al principio los resultados eran poco favorables y desanimadores, pero finalmente defendí y saqué la máxima calificación posible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Como este no es un post técnico, simplemente voy a listar algunas cosas que aprendí de la &lt;em&gt;experiencia&lt;/em&gt; de haber hecho la tesis&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Escribir el libro desde el principio&lt;/strong&gt;: El primer consejo de Benjamín Barán (mi excelente tutor!) y que como todo novato traté de seguir la primera
semana pero no había caso.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Escribir el libro de tesis (después de terminar todo lo otro) es una de esas actividades en la vida que hacen que literalmente 
cualquier &lt;em&gt;otra&lt;/em&gt; actividad se vuelva inmediatamente algo infinitamente fascinante. Yo atribuyo esto al hecho de que uno ya estuvo lidiando con el tema por tanto
tiempo y desde tantos puntos de vista, que volver a encarar el problema resuelto pierde todo el atractivo y la emoción de todo lo que uno ignora.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A la madrugada se programa mejor&lt;/strong&gt;: Al menos en mi caso. Infinita pelea con Mamá y Papá (“voy a dormir temprano!! te juro!!”).&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Esto es algo personal y estoy 100% seguro de que cada uno tiene su horario de iluminación y lastimosamente el mío es entre las 2 y 4 de la mañana. No sé como
explicar la sensación de silencio y quietud que solamente se puede sentir a estas horas de la madrugada. Para mí es como que toda la ciudad se calla y me deja
pensar con más claridad. No hay interrupciones… no hay ruidos… no hay apuros… sinceramente hasta ahora nunca logro concentrarme tan profundamente en otro
horario.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TODOS te pueden dar feedback SUPER VALIOSO!&lt;/strong&gt;: Fue una sorpresa cuando me di cuenta de esto.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Mi tema de tesis es “Optimización por Enjambre de Partículas en Problemas de Muchos Objetivos”, lo que “simplificado y resumido” significa utilizar un programa
que simula un montón (enjambre) de elementos que se llaman partículas, para tratar de resolver problemas de muchas dimensiones (osea… más complejos que otros 
problemas), y esto lo hace inspirado en el movimiento de animales como las abejas y aves que exploran una zona de manera colectiva. Prueben decirle eso a 
cualquiera y van a conocer la expresión facial que expresa con total claridad “te volviste loco chera’a”.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Aun así, cuando estás con un dilema específico, la gente que está dispuesta a escucharte un rato y dejarte traducir toda la jerga a conceptos más simples puede 
ayudarte de una manera impresionante a ver otro punto de vista que, por estar muy metido en el problema, no te resultaba obvio. Me cuesta dar un ejemplo específico
que ilustre esto de forma espectacular, pero para mí uno de los más memorables fue hablar con Rocio (mi hermana) acerca de un tema nada relacionado a la tesis.
No recuerdo el tema de conversación exacto, pero recuerdo que ella me dijo la frase “todos esos frasquitos tienen un uso, no importa si es chico, por lo menos una
tierrita entra”. Esa frase arbitraria por algún motivo hizo &lt;em&gt;click&lt;/em&gt; en mi cabeza y me llevó a la solución de un bug que tenía en mi representación de hipercubos
n-dimensionales en python.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;¡Investigar es divertido!&lt;/strong&gt;: Este es un punto simple de explicar para mí. Cuando era chiquito y no sabía cómo funcionaba algo, siempre le preguntaba a Papá 
“¿cómo funciona la heladera? porque… osea… CREA frio ¿entendés?” “¿la fotocopiadora tiene un ojo o algo así verdad?” “¿cómo lo que las llaves son todas parecidas
pero una nomas abre cada candado?”. Era prácticamente un juego para mi… Investigar es la expansión de ese juego!!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#El #GAMEDEVPY&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yo defendía la tesis un lunes… y el jueves de esa misma semana tenía que dar una charla acerca de música para videojuegos en un evento organizado por IGDA Paraguay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El evento salió muchísimo mejor de lo que esperába todos, y estuve mostrando los juegos que hice con Fer (para saber quién es Fer, lee los posts viejos!). Fue 
muchísima gente e incluso ese fin de semana hablamos del evento en radios locales! Espero que pronto tengamos eventos de este tipo nuevamente!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Para evitar alargar mucho este (ya medio kilométrico post) les dejo el &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/1iDo7U9VR7Y&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; de la charla y &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.443927162434811.1073741833.301346146692914&amp;amp;type=3&quot;&gt;fotos&lt;/a&gt; del evento!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#La vida después de la tesis (World of Warcraft)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Una breve lista de las cosas principales estoy haciendo por ahora:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investigando el mismo tema de la tesis.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trabajando a tiempo completo.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Preparando documentos y cosas para una posible beca.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Programando videojuegos! Con la gente de &lt;a href=&quot;http://arsisteam.com&quot;&gt;arsis&lt;/a&gt;, estamos preparando una versión mucho más increíble de Bacterias (quizás con otro nombre!).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jugando! (Principalmente World of Warcraft, pero de una manera MUCHO más responsable y sensata que cuando estaba en el colegio!).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
                                <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2015 07:17:00 +0100</pubDate>
                                <link>http://localhost:4000//ingenieria-la-vida-y-wow/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//ingenieria-la-vida-y-wow/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Hello World! (again)</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello again my fellow readers!! (Hi Mom!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been a long time since my last post and I just wanted to post a little update on what’s going on with my life and this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I’ve bought a new domain (&lt;a href=&quot;torresmateo.com&quot;&gt;torresmateo.com&lt;/a&gt;) and moved the blog here (you can still use the old url though, but it will just redirect here). This means that all those hundreds of thousands of facebook comments (for a total sum of 10 through all posts) are gone and comments are disabled until I come across a system that I like and it’s not so JavaScript related.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, a brief update on what I’ve been doing since August. I decided to organise this a little bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#College and Work Related Stuff&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been working on my thesis and it seems I’m on the last mile of that road. I’ve published a paper in the process, which I’ll link in a future post. It’s about solving multi-dimensional optimisation problems using algorithms based on a particle swarm meta-heuristic. Cool right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also been working in web development as always, it’s still fun, thanks for asking :D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#Game Related Stuff&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now to the important business&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;igda-paraguay&quot;&gt;IGDA Paraguay&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here in Paraguay the game development industry is almost nonexistent. I mean, there are many game developers and a lot of them are incredibly capable, but sadly there is almost no market here and we have some serious limitations like not being able to sell in Google Play (unless we partner with someone from another country).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The IGDA (International Game Developers Association) is the largest non-profit membership organization serving individuals that create games and now Paraguay is a proud member with its own chapter. We are starting making some noise here and for the first time (that I know of) we’re getting some serious attention from a lot of people. The videogame market is growing and a lot of developers, designers and artists are getting to know each other and it seems to me that very soon we’ll see Paraguayan games shining out there. You can get updates on our chapter &lt;a href=&quot;http://facebook.com/igdapy&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been given the honor of collaborating on this amazing project as secretary!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-personal-projects&quot;&gt;My Personal Projects&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While not writing this blog, or writing my thesis, or working, or doing survival related things like eating or sleeping…. I’ve been programming some games (kind of).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wolfenstein-3d-clone&quot;&gt;Wolfenstein 3D Clone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project started as a way to teach myself “proper” 3D and OpenGL. I though “I should start with the very basic”. I know an infinite number of clones of this game are already out there, but I don’t care, the process was unbelievably fun and I learned a lot. I’m not sure about releasing this because there’s nothing really exciting about the game itself. Also, I didn’t make a lot of effort in the assets of the game and it doesn’t look very pretty. I’m not sure… maybe I’ll do it in the future. Who knows?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mini-engine&quot;&gt;Mini Engine&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After finishing the Wolf3D clone, I wanted to keep learning OpenGL and I came across &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/user/thebennybox&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; YouTube Channel (which I then realised contains a tutorial on how to do a Wolf3D clone, kudos to me for not googling before coding!). It really is an invaluable source of knowledge for beginners who want to build a 3D game engine from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mobile-project&quot;&gt;Mobile Project&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest project is a mobile (or rather multi-platform) game. I’m using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cocos2d-x.org/&quot;&gt;Cocos2d-x&lt;/a&gt;, which is an open source 2D (and now 3D) game engine written in C++. So far it’s been amazingly easy and it lets me focus on the game mechanics rather than deal with the rendering and technical issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main idea is to make a simple game but actually finish it and release it as a commercial product this year, or maybe in 2016. We’ll see. I’ll probably make a dev blog starting in march, when I expect to be working at least half time on this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;this-blog&quot;&gt;This Blog&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original idea remains (except the “one post every two weeks” part to be realistic). But there are some changes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be writing some tutorials on some topics that I had a very difficult time to come across or had to read from several unrelated sources to understand. I think of it as a remainder and hopefully it’ll help someone else. They will mainly be about how to program this or that using Cocos2d-x or how to do specific things using OpenGL and GLSL, but there will also be tutorials on asset generation. So far, I’ve decided to start with these:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Blender Tutorial: How to setup a fully automated Isometric tile generation Scene (a tutorial for absolute Blender newbies like me). This is mostly a Python tutorial.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to automate a tilesheet generation in Photoshop and Gimp for Tiled (using scripts).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to easily make an isometric scene in Cocos2d-x.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know when I’ll be releasing these tutorials, but the first one is already started, so it certainly wont be six months (I think).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s 100% true is the next post will be about the last complete game Fer and I made in College. I’ll try my best to post it by the end of January, but so far my schedule projections for this blogs are nothing but lies. If you like to give some feedback on this, feel free to &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:torresmateo@gmail.com&quot;&gt;e-mail&lt;/a&gt; me. Please refer tho the post you’re talking about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aaaaaaaaand I think that’s all for now, see you next time!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                                <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2015 06:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://localhost:4000//hello-world-again/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//hello-world-again/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Backgammon Madness</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;Artificial Intelligence is the heart of a Player vs. PC game, and there are a lot of options to have a program &lt;em&gt;thinking&lt;/em&gt;. For instance,
if you have to make a game like &lt;a href=&quot;/ui-design/&quot;&gt;Bacteria&lt;/a&gt;, the obvious choice is
&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alpha%E2%80%93beta_pruning&quot;&gt;Alpha-Beta pruning&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-story&quot;&gt;The Story&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The assignment Fer and I had was &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Backgammon&quot;&gt;Backgammon&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a board game with checkers and dices. The
main goal is to move your checkers from your “house” to the opponent’s. In your turn you throw a pair of dices, and move the checkers forward.
If you’ve got the same result in both dices, you earn a double turn, moving four times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s actually a boring game, compared to chess, but Fer and I learned how to play, and even watched YouTube videos of the world championship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When this assignment was given, one of the requirements was to use alpha-beta pruning for the AI. It didn’t feel right to me, because adding
dices to the mix leaves you with a lot of randomness. Of course you can modify alpha-beta to deal with the randomness, but as I’ve said above,
there are A LOT of options, and it’s part of the art of problem solving to pick the right tool for the job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In class, I asked our teacher about this, and he didn’t answer my question. I stayed after class to him again, and we had an argument about the
right algorithm to use for the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-implementation&quot;&gt;The implementation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graphically, it’s the same as &lt;a href=&quot;/ui-design/&quot;&gt;Bacteria&lt;/a&gt;. Even the mouse handler is 90% taken from our previous
implementation, we used color masks and sprites. &lt;a href=&quot;http://alleg.sourceforge.net/&quot;&gt;Allegro&lt;/a&gt; was also the library we used again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference was AI. We had to learn some useful strategies for backgammon. The game has two logical stages. In the first stage, the opponent
can block your checkers, and this means a lot of computation towards avoiding that, and focusing on desirable board configurations. In the
second stage it’s simply a “race”, the first player to reach the opponent’s “home” wins the game. We implemented a weight based heuristic for
both stages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first heuristic was focused in achieving good board configurations, we had points for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Distance to the opponent’s home (low priority)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid blocked checkers (medium priority)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Block opponent’s checkers (medium priority)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Occupy six adjacent columns (high priority)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were other aspects, but these four are the most important. The last one was added after watching a lot of (boring) backgammon games online.
Professional players seemed to aim for a particular board configuration. When you have two or more checkers in the same column, the opponent can’t
block your checkers in that column, so having six consecutive columns occupied means you own a “wall” of columns that the other player can’t
pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second stage has the following priorities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Distance to the opponent’s home (high priority)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Everything else (no priority)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, it’s focused on reaching the opponent’s home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-tournament&quot;&gt;The tournament&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main goal of this implementation was to make every team challenge other’s programs. It was fun, at first we won because most of our classmates’
programs weren’t finished. We ended with 3 complete games (best of 3), the first two we won 2-0, and the last one (the final game of the tournament)
was our program against Rafael Arias Michel and Daniel Ruffinelli’s implementation, I’ll refer to them as &lt;em&gt;Rafa&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Ruffo&lt;/em&gt; from now on unless they
ask me not to, in which case I’ll probably keep calling them &lt;em&gt;Rafa&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Ruffo&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They had a nice implementation in GTK, and if I remember correctly they had implemented Alpha-Beta Pruning. Our program won the first match, the second
one we lost! By that moment we had an audience (about 6 classmates who were interested enough to stay and watch a bunch of nerds cheering for their
own implementation of a complete boring board game). The last game was interesting, both programs made mistakes, specially at the end. We could not tell
who had the advantage until the very end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily we won :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video-and-code&quot;&gt;Video and Code&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last, but not least, here’s the video of me playing (and winning!) against my own implementation. The interface this time isn’t as elaborated as in
Bacteria, but the main reasons were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The objective was not to make a playable PC vs Player game, we did it for completeness.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Backgammon is boring.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We focused on the PC vs PC tournament instead of Interface and/or Design, I think it looks OK though.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Backgammon is boring.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Did I mention how boring Backgammon is?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WARNING:&lt;/strong&gt; It’s about 4 minutes of myself playing a boring game :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/dKyYiN4sj7s?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and as always… the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/torresmateo/Backgammon&quot;&gt;code&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                                <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2014 06:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://localhost:4000//backgammon/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//backgammon/</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Bacteria, Part 2: Gameplay, Drag &amp; Drop and other Stuff</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the second part of the Bacteria development, I’ll focus in gameplay, and the technique we used for implementing drag and drop
with Allegro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gameplay&quot;&gt;Gameplay&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I’ll give a little introduction of what gameplay is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Gameplay is the specific way in which players interact with a game, and in particular with video games. Gameplay is the pattern defined 
through the game rules, connection between player and the game, challenges and overcoming them, plot and player’s connection with it. 
Video game gameplay is distinct from graphics, and audio elements.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;div style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;&amp;#8213;Random Dude in Wikipedia&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That should be clear enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our game, we wanted the player to focus in the strategic part of the game, and not to deal with an uncomfortable way of interacting
with objects on the screen. In our previous games the player had to learn a bunch of “complicated” controls to do things, and it wasn’t
fun to play that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;drag--drop&quot;&gt;Drag &amp;amp; Drop&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Bacteria is a board game, the intuitive way to interact with it is obviously the mouse. Here’s a list of the things you can do with
any mouse:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Move pointer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Click.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Right-Click.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty limited. I didn’t include &lt;em&gt;scroll&lt;/em&gt; in that list because (sadly) not all mice have a scroll wheel. So, handling the mouse is 
not as simple as it can appear at first sight… aaaand right-clicking sucks in a board game… so… here’s our new list:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Move pointer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Click.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But wait!! If you think about it, there are special things about the click event, and it’s all about timing. In every mouse based interface
you have more options:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Double-click:&lt;/strong&gt; Click two times, fast. It’s like clicking, but if almost every time a single-click is &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;select&lt;/code&gt;, double click is &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;open&lt;/code&gt; or, 
in a more general way: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;interact&lt;/code&gt; with the double-clicked element.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drag-and-Drop:&lt;/strong&gt; It’s done by pressing on the element, moving the mouse while still pressing the mouse button, and then releasing the button
in another area in the screen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These options are called &lt;em&gt;gestures&lt;/em&gt;. We were interested in &lt;em&gt;Drag-and-Drop&lt;/em&gt;, because it’s the simplest way to “move” one object over the scene.
The basic idea is click and hold one of the little bacteria, and somehow give the player the feeling that s/he is “holding” the object as long
as the mouse button is pressed. We implemented this feature by doing the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On mouse press:&lt;/strong&gt; Quickly swap the bacteria with a “phantom” version, useful to know the original position in the board. Also, replace the
mouse pointer, our choice was the same pointer with a bacteria attached to it, so wherever the player moved the mouse, the bacteria seemed
to be glued to the pointer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On mouse release:&lt;/strong&gt; Swap the pointer image to the original (the one without the bacteria attached). If the player released in a valid cell, 
the original cell now looks like an empty cell, and the new cell now hold a bacteria. If the player released in any other place, the phantom
version returns to be the normal bacteria.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It worked like a charm!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s an image showing the empty cell, the “phantom” bacteria , the “infected” cell, and both pointers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/bacteria-part-2/blue_bacteria.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Blue Bacteria&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;artificial-intelligence&quot;&gt;Artificial Intelligence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some words about the intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, we knew absolutely NOTHING about game theory at the time, and I think we did pretty well taking that into account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our implementation was a tree-like decision structure. We started by assuming the enemy played the best he could, and the AI moves acted accordingly.
It’s pretty clever after reading the code almost 4 years later =). It’s not very hard to beat the computer with this AI, but not ultra-easy though, 
it takes to think at least two moves ahead to win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;finally&quot;&gt;Finally&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well… I wrote a LOT about Bacteria, and after reading it myself I decided it was long and boring, so I erased all of it and instead made a 
video of myself showing what I think are the best parts of this game:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Menus… they look AWESOME!!.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Board Editor.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Game.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Instruction Pages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not a long video, and I lose (in my defense, the purpose of this wasn’t for me to win, but to show the features).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/H9hrEwQNlbw?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;to-be-continued&quot;&gt;To be continued…&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next post is not about Bacteria. It’s about Backgammon, but only the AI part, since all the rest is pretty similar to Bacteria, the interesting
part is the intelligence. I plan to make another video for that post, since it’s much easier for me to show the features that way, and maybe
it’s a better experience to you to actually see the interactivity and other things that can’t be seen properly in still images.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                                <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2014 06:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
                                <link>http://localhost:4000//bacteria-part-2/</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//bacteria-part-2/</guid>
                        </item>
                
        </channel>
</rss>
